Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we continue with
part two of our series on yoga
and we start with the question:
which of the 50 different yoga styles
have been shown to be best?
Should doctors recommend
their patients do yoga?
As you've seen in my last videos,
the difficulties associated
with recommending yoga
stem from the low quality
of scientific evidence available
regarding its effects.
Oddly, this lack of evidence is
partly due to a common failure
among researchers to define
what they actually studied.
They just say yoga without
defining what they mean.
And different types of yoga differ
greatly in what they demand
in terms of physical strength,
depth of meditation,
breathing control, and
spiritual component.
Yet it's very common for
reports of studies not to define
which type they used.
This not only makes it hard to
compare results between studies,
it also makes it very hard
to translate any findings
to the bedside
when counseling patients.
Yoga is broadly defined
as a mind-body practice
composed of physical postures,
breathing techniques,
and meditation,
and so if researchers say
they put yoga to the test,
you'd assume all three components
would be present.
However some studies use
meditation only and call it yoga,
with no postures or breathing.
Others only examine breathing
exercises and call it yoga.
Others consider yoga only postures,
and still others say they're studying
forms of yoga without
any of the three components.
And so if a study
shows no benefit,
does that really mean yoga as
commonly practiced didn't help?
And if a study does show benefit,
what exactly do you tell
patients to do to achieve it?
We can take some comfort
in the fact that a review
entitled "Is one yoga style
better than another?"
attempted to compare
the effects of the more than
50 different yoga styles
used in hundreds of trials,
and they concluded that there
was no apparent winner
in terms of whether
the results turned out positive,
so to a certain extent they
may be interchangeable.
I've talked about the need
to have active control to see
if there's some benefit to yoga
beyond just the exercise component,
but such controls may still
not deal with confounders
such as socialization.
Yoga usually involves
going to classes.
So you can imagine if you were
studying the effects of yoga
on something like depression,
does breaking routine,
getting out, and
meeting other people
have any effect,
independent of the yoga?
Sadly for depression,
yoga doesn't even seem to have
a benefit compared to doing nothing.
Yoga does appear
to be helpful with anxiety,
but not for people anxious
to the extent
that they're actually diagnosed
with an anxiety disorder.
And all the anxiety benefit
from yoga appears to just be
from the physical activity,
since there appears to be
no benefit compared
to other types of exercise.
So unfortunately, yoga does
not appear to be effective
for mood and anxiety disorders.
A review on the effects of yoga
on depressive symptoms
in people with mental
disorders in general,
including conditions like
PTSD or schizophrenia,
found no significant effect compared
to things like social support
that offer the same kind
of attention, or to doing nothing,
but did find an effect compared
to so-called "waitlist" controls.
See, unlike in studies of drug effects
where a placebo sugar pill
is relatively straightforward,
selection of a control condition
is much more complex for
behavioral interventions like yoga,
and one common solution is
a passive control such as a waitlist.
Basically, people are randomized
to either yoga or onto a waitlist
where they'll still get yoga
but have to wait awhile.
Now that's better than having
no control group at all,
since it still controls
for the passage of time,
meaning whether or not
your condition would
have just gotten better
naturally on its own, but doesn't
really control for the placebo effect.
If instead you were just told
you were entering a study
to see if some exercises may help,
and then unbeknownst to you
randomized to do yoga
versus some sort of sham yoga,
then you would have the same
kind of expectation either way.
But if you know going into it
you're going to get yoga now,
which may help,
or yoga in 6 months and you
end up in the waitlist control,
this may spuriously amplify
the difference in treatment effect
because people assigned
to the waitlist may expect
to not get better
without active treatment.
For example, here's a study
for yoga on urinary incontinence.
Women were randomized to 6 weeks
of yoga or a waitlist control group.
After 6 weeks, the incontinence
frequency decreased
by 70% in the yoga therapy
versus only 13% fewer episodes
in the control group.
But it's possible that the women
in the yoga group reported
some benefits due to what's
called an expectation bias
because they expected
yoga to be helpful.
So based on the body
of evidence, one might say
there's insufficient good quality
evidence to judge
whether yoga is useful for
women with urinary incontinence.
But what we'd like to see
are studies comparing yoga
to time-and-attention
control interventions ---
some alternative to yoga
that entails the same amount
of time and attention,
so people don't even know
they're in a control group.
Now the question arises:
who cares if the benefits
from a yoga intervention
are due to the placebo effect
or expectation bias?
A benefit is a benefit.
As long as people are
getting better, who cares?
But it would be nice to know
if yoga really helps or not,
and here we go.
Women with urinary incontinence
were randomly assigned
to a yoga group or a rigorous
time-and-attention control group
involving nonspecific
muscle stretching
and strengthening exercises.
There are two different types
of urinary incontinence:
urgency incontinence, defined
as an involuntary loss of urine
associated with a sudden
strong desire to urinate,
or stress incontinence,
where an activity
such as sneezing
triggers an involuntary leak.
Three months of yoga didn't
seem to significantly help
overall incontinence,
but it did seem to help
with stress incontinence,
decreasing by an average
of 61% in the yoga group
versus only 35% in controls
with no significant changes
in urgency incontinence.
In our next study,
we look at how sham acupuncture
underscores the necessity
of controlling for
expectancy effects.
Yoga as therapy:
When is it helpful?
The scientific literature on yoga
is limited in scope and quality.
I've talked about the long list
of issues that plague
so many of the yoga trials,
but let's continue down
the list of conditions
to get a sense of the best
available balance of evidence.
For example, yoga as a therapy
for irritable bowel syndrome.
Evidence from randomized controlled
trials found that yoga beat out drugs
and was equally effective as
moderate-intensity walking,
so whichever form
of exercise you prefer.
What about yoga for
Inflammatory Bowel Disease?
Since stress can be a trigger,
might yoga help?
In a trial of yoga as an add-on
therapy for adolescents
with inflammatory bowel disease,
it didn't seem to help at all.
But in a trial of yoga
vs written self-care advice
for adults with ulcerative colitis,
12 weeks of yoga
induced a stronger increase
in quality of life,
and also reduced disease activity
even three months
after the study ended.
Now, the so-called self-care
group was really just handed
a couple general self-care books,
so the two treatments, yoga vs
self-care, were not matched at all
for time intensity, feeling part
of a group or for therapist contact---
each of which are likely to have
the "yoga" arm more likely
to nonspecifically improve
their quality of life.
So, yes, yoga might be effective
in improving quality
of life in ulcerative colitis,
however, the benefits may be
no different to other group
exercise, for example.
Indeed, there have been 11
human studies on the influence
of moderate exercise programs
upon disease activity
in chronic inflammatory
bowel disease,
and all 11 report benefit in terms
of reduced disease activity.
Using passive controls doesn't
account for expectancy effects,
attention given to the study
subjects, and the time spent,
the investment that
the participants put in.
Here's an excellent
example of why having
more active control groups
is so important.
This details a series of studies
on nonpharmacological
interventions for
menopausal hot flashes.
For example, randomized
to 8 weeks of acupuncture,
8 weeks of sham acupuncture,
or nothing, just usual care.
Sham acupuncture is when
they still stick needles in you,
but shallowly and not in
traditional acupuncture points.
There was also a study
of 10 weeks of yoga classes,
or the attention control (health
and wellness education classes)
which lasted just
as long as the yoga
and were done in the same kind
of group social setting.
Here's what they found.
The hot flashes in the usual care
group, the passive control
where they didn't do anything
special stayed pretty stable.
But the real acupuncture
worked way better,
But so did the
sham acupuncture.
So yoga and acupuncture
both worked just as well,
but so did the non-yoga
and fake acupuncture.
There just appeared to be
a general placebo effect
such that women in
all five intervention groups
benefited simply
by being in a study.
That's why it's always better
to have the control groups
do something, so you can
have some confidence
at least some of the effect
of your intervention is real.
But hey, at least
they had control groups.
This study, "Twelve-Minute
Daily Yoga Regimen Reverses
Osteoporotic Bone Loss"
caused quite a stir.
We know that when
it comes to bone health,
it's use it or lose it: exercise
early and exercise often.
Physical activity is
a widely accessible, low cost,
and highly modifiable
contributor to bone health.
Exercise transmits forces
through the skeleton,
generating signals that are detected
by your bone building cells.
This is why the National
Osteoporosis Foundation,
the International
and other agencies recommend
weight-bearing exercises
for the prevention of osteoporosis.
These include high impact
exercises, such as jumping,
aerobics, and running,
as well as lower impact exercises,
such as walking and weight training,
to create these mechanical signals
that spark bone growth.
Lower impact activities
such as yoga
are generally not considered
bone-building.
That's why the results
of this study were so surprising.
It was a study of
internet-recruited volunteers
comparing bone mineral density
changes before and after yoga.
The researchers devised
a 12-minute DVD of 12 yoga poses
that they believed would stimulate
increased bone density
in the spine and both
parts of the hip.
But in the end, out of the 741
patients recruited at the beginning,
only a few dozen actually sent in
their bone scans as instructed.
So that's only like 5%,
so they lost 95% of the people
that originally started.
You can totally imagine how
those who got positive results
were more likely
to send them in,
and the others that failed
just kind of slunk away,
so I don't consider this
convincing evidence.
Now the authors
had the attitude of
"Hey, look, so what do
you got to lose?
The side effects of yoga are all
good, so why not give it a try?"
Well, what you have to lose
is the opportunity
to do higher impact exercise
that has more decisive evidence
of bone benefit.
And all the side effects
are not necessarily good.
There have been vertebral
compression fractures
associated with yoga.
In this series of nine cases
from the Mayo Clinic
they described spinal compression
fractures occurring a month to years
after initiating yoga-associated
spinal flexion exercises.
Both scientific and media reports
continue to advertise yoga
as a bone protective activity,
but there's a need for selectivity
in yoga poses in populations
at increased fracture risk.
And four of the nine patients
developed a fracture
in the setting of a normal or
near-normal bone mineral density.
So maybe everyone should
be careful with these.
Yoga-related injuries
are not uncommon,
resulting in thousands of
emergency room visits a year,
and approximately 5% of those
are coming in with fractures.
I'll try to put that
injury rate in context,
comparing yoga
to other physical activities next.
Even though for certain
health conditions
we have not reached
a point where we can say
there's good scientific evidence
that yoga is beneficial,
many patients do seem to benefit.
And isn't that what matters?
I mean even in the studies
that show the benefit
is mainly a placebo effect,
does this really matter?
I mean, after all,
this editorial asserted,
yoga therapy has never been
shown to have adverse effects.
But that's simply not true.
About 2,000 yoga-related
injuries have been seen
in hospital emergency rooms
every year from 2001 to 2014.
It looks like only one fatality
has ever been reported
in the medical literature,
but if you look at the case report,
a 16-year-old girl collapsing
with a ruptured lung
following voluntary mouth-to-mouth
yoga breathing exercises
with a teen-age boy in the hall ---
that can hardly be characterized
as a typical yoga practice.
There are tragic rare cases
tied to actual yoga,
like this quad rupture in a young
woman, or God, a femoral fracture.
The femur is the bone in your thigh --
longest, strongest and
heaviest bone in the body.
Typically, you only see
femur fractures
with trauma such as car crashes,
but here it was just a guy
practicing this yoga posture
when he heard a large cracking
sound and felt immense pain
because, yikes,
this is what happened.
Now two weeks earlier
he had felt pain in his thigh
that he just thought
was muscle strain,
but bone biopsies showed
evidence of previous microfractures.
So it sounds like he had
been overdoing it,
weakening it before
the final crack.
So I guess the bottom line
is that people should listen
to their bodies and not
push themselves too far.
Now, in my last video
I talked about the risk
of spinal compression fractures,
particularly those
with weakened bones,
osteopenia or osteoporosis.
Poses causing hyperflexion
and hyperextension of the spine
should probably be avoided.
These were the poses tied
to injury in a few dozen cases
of musculoskeletal injuries
described at the Mayo Clinic.
But case reports and
series of case reports
are really just kind of
glorified anecdotes.
I mean, they don't give you an
overall sense of the safety of yoga.
If you look at randomized
controlled yoga trials,
there's actually no significant
difference in injury rates
between the yoga groups
and the control groups
that used some other sort
of exercise intervention.
Now, this may not
necessarily translate out
into real-world experience,
given the short duration
of yoga in these clinical trials --
as little as a single day --
and the fact that they may be
more closely supervised
with more highly trained teachers.
That's why large-scale surveys
like this can be helpful,
looking at thousands of people
taking yoga classes.
Looks like about 30% of yoga
class attendees had experienced
some type of adverse event,
most commonly just something
mild like muscle aches,
but some individuals did
experience more severe events
which caused them to stop going.
Many causes were associated
with overexertion and overdoing
and starting out in
poor physical condition.
This systematic review included
nine observational studies
with 9000+ yoga practitioners
and 9000+ non-yoga practitioners
from the US, Europe,
Asia, and Australia.
A considerable proportion of yoga
practitioners experienced injuries
or other adverse events;
however most were
mild and transient
and risks were comparable to
those of non-yoga practitioners.
The risk of yoga-associated
injuries was estimated
as 1.45 per thousand hours
of yoga practice,
much lower than in higher-impact
sports activities such as soccer.
Compared to 1.5 for yoga,
runners have like 2.5 injuries
per thousand hours,
soccer 3.7,
5 for tennis,
and an hour of yoga is more
than 5 times safer than skiing.
Here's where yoga falls
on the spectrum.
Yoga appears much safer,
for example, than aerobic funk.
On the other hand, yoga
practitioners may suffer
an increased risk
of meniscus injury,
the main stabilizing and
cushioning cartilage in the knee.
Yoga was found associated
with significantly higher risk
of meniscus injury compared with
activities such as badminton,
jogging, and climbing hills.
Some fundamental yoga postures,
like the lotus position,
can be hard on the knees.
Yes, yoga poses can undoubtedly
improve the flexibility of the knee,
but immoderate joint movement
can pose a serious threat.
The bottom line is like any other
type of physical activity:
yoga carries a risk of injury.
Exercise is indeed medicine,
but like any medicine, it must be
prescribed appropriately.
Many patients rely on their yoga
practice for stress reduction,
so it's important to be mindful
that being injured
is the last thing you need.
The higher-risk yoga poses
appear to include
headstands, shoulder stands,
lotus and half lotus,
forward bends, backward
bends, and handstands.
And so beginners
should beware,
with particular attention
paid to the spine
as this is where the highest
numbers of injuries occur.
Hot yoga deserves
special mention.
The extreme heat and
intensity of Bikram yoga
may make it inappropriate
for older adults and people
with medical conditions.
But there are case reports like
this one of sudden cardiac arrest
even in a healthy 35-year-old.
Pregnancy is an especially
vulnerable time for heat exposure.
With the increased risk
of spinal defects
and possibly
other birth defects
among fetuses exposed
to excessive heat,
pregnant women should avoid
practicing hot yoga during pregnancy.
Maternal hyperthermia, whether
from a sauna or electric blankets,
had nearly a 2-fold increased risk
of spinal and brain malformations.
For example, pregnant women
who use hot tubs
increased the risk
of bearing babies
with their intestines
outside their bodies
or being born
without a brain.
As any other physical
or mental practice,
yoga should be practiced carefully
under the guidance
of a qualified instructor.
Beginners should avoid
extreme practices
such as headstand, lotus
position, forceful breathing.
Individuals with
medical preconditions
should work with their
physician and yoga teacher
to appropriately adapt postures.
For example, patients with glaucoma
should avoid upside-down positions,
and patients with compromised bones
should avoid forceful yoga practices,
and practices like
voluntary vomiting
should perhaps be
avoided completely.
What?
It's evidently a common
practice in traditional yoga.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.